Inventory of the Joseph B. Mittelman miscellaneous papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph B. Mittelman miscellaneous papers
1941-1945
46026
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, memorabilia (0.5 linear feet)
The papers include a History of 9th Division operations in Germany from 1944 to 1945 and memorabilia from the European Theater in World War II, including a helmet and other items from Nazi headquarters at Berchtesgaden, Germany.
Mittelman, Joseph B.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1946.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
A First lieutenant in the United States Army during World War II, Mittelman was the division historian of the 9th Infantry Division.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers include a History of 9th Division operations in Germany from 1944 to 1945 and memorabilia from the European Theater in World War II, including a helmet and other items from Nazi headquarters at Berchtesgaden, Germany.
Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 9th.; National socialism.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Germany.
- Collected Memorabilia
  - Piece of tile from Hitler's stove at Berchtesgaden, June 1945 (Box 1)
  - Left marble corner of Hitler's big window at Berchtesgaden, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Plastiglass remnants of a Nazi plane destroyed on ground found near Munich, June 1945 (Box 1)
  - Rommel's Afrika Corps helmet captured by the 9th Division, undated (Memorabilia-cabinet 1)
  - Boat found under Hilter's bathtub in his ruined house in Berchtesgaden, June 1945 (Box 1)
  - Face of clock from the SS Barracks, Berchtesgaden, found under rubble, June 1945 (Box 1)
  - Black case and contents, June 1945 (Box 1)
    Contents include: kit case from Ingolstadt signal warehouse, pipes from Wehrmacht Barracks, Ingolstadt, wrenches from signal warehouse, Ingolstadt, pencil from captured stocks, Ingolstadt, and a key to the Ingolstadt ordnance plant
- Hand made book commemorating Nazi Party principles found at Göring's headquarters, Gabersee, Bavaria, 1945 (Box 1)
- Scattered issues of the San Francisco Examiner, Chronicle, Call Bulletin, News and other miscellaneous periodicals, undated (Box 1)